so the four noble truths
you were saying
four aspects
there are four aspects of one insight
which is
the uh the way out of suffering
there isn't suffering you you see
how to escape it without trying to get
rid of it
but first you must be able to well
that's the thing yeah so um if you want
to understand the way out of suffering
first you need to understand the
suffering and uh people can't understand the
and uh people can't understand the
suffering because they can't give up the
pressure the need the urge to get rid of it to
the need the urge to get rid of it to
manage it to prevent it
and that's where it comes down to okay
so so what type of suffering
you shouldn't be trying to prevent or
get rid of
because sometimes people can now mistake
that thinking okay like self-torture or
extreme asceticism and so on starving
yourself no that might be helpful if that's what
no that might be helpful if that's what
brings that right type of suffering
for which you need to know first what
the right type of suffering is and it's
the suffering on the level of whatever's
felt so
so
you need to endure
and not act out of
the pressure towards more pleasure when
you're feeling agreeable
you need to endure and not act out of
the pressure
towards getting rid
getting rid
of the pain when you're feeling
disagreeable you need to give up and not
act out of the pressure
to basically ignore
the when it's neither pleasant or unpleasant
when it's neither pleasant or unpleasant
state of feeling that you have
and that's that's the hardest to do
because that's why people find sense
restraint hard
because you have to endure that pressure
that's why they find it hard to not try
to manage the suffering or explain it or
psychologize it because you have to do
the pressure
and that's why they have find it really
really hard um to not distract
themselves when they're feeling neither
pleasant or unpleasant
to not find something to do
to not be find some
activity to keep them occupied because
then it just becomes very unpleasant
see if you do things on that level and
don't act out there you don't need to do
any asceticism at all
that is that is the truth tapas as the
weather said that is the true enduring
towards the purification through that
endurance but it's actually much easier
but it's actually much easier
to work yourself up
and build up a determination and
endure this extreme physical
discomforts and and and and
practices
as long as you don't endure them on that
emotional level of
comfort discomfort and mutual feeling
that's where the dread is
and that's what i said said
the the asceticism is as misguided as
sensuality just in a different direction
both equally missed the point which is
that middle ground of
yeah what is the current enduring
feeling and what's my attitude towards
it am i welcoming it delighting it am i
trying to get rid of it
psychologize it manage it explain it
ignore it distract myself from it
because i can't bear the boredom
all right in do things on that level
as i said before you will not need much
of an instruction then because you
already have the right basis
and the certain
obvious aspects of your situation will
become like revealed
such as right okay so yeah i am liable
to this suffering and everything i've
been doing so far
has not uprooted it hasn't has not even
been in the direction of uprooting that
suffering it was only in the level of
management and distraction from it
and the dharma is directed that
direction of uprooting so it's
completely the opposite way of
completely against the stream and the
directions that have been going so far
but for that you first need to endure it
on that right level that's when you have
to understand the suffering first
in order to see the way out
so you need to stop trying to get rid of
the suffering and manage it in order to
understand it you need to allow it to be
endure in order for it to be understood
because it takes time to understand it
and you sort of deny that time by trying
by covering up the suffering or getting
rid of it or or just managing it to to
to not be felt anymore
but you know it will come back so you
haven't really uprooted its nature
you haven't pulled out the the source
the roots while it's there in front of
the front
yeah in your face yeah exactly yeah
so that's that's the true asceticism of
the correct kind can you endure the pain
without expressing it without trying to get rid
expressing it without trying to get rid
of it without psychologizing it
without hateful thoughts
without turning away and ignoring it can
you just stay with it
can you endure the suffering
without doing anything on account of it
yeah because now okay now i'm going to endure
because now okay now i'm going to endure
the song exactly so i can get rid of it
yeah so you start enjoying the suffering
maybe for one second rightly and then
there's two next second you fall into
now i'm enduring it because i want to
get rid of it
so what do i do then
like well
you include that into your endurance or
suffering that you don't want to get rid
of
because yes you can endure the suffering
rightly but then you can endure it
wrongly if it got uh
if you become motivated
by different reasons such as you're not
enduring it for its own sake you're
doing it to get rid of it which means
right well now i'm back on to the old
attitude
so how do you stop that by enduring it
it's not going to be perfect
but as long as you know that you're
supposed to endure it without acting out
of it even that mind that makes that
endurance as acting out of it will come
down if you don't act out of it
and if you endured it sufficiently
enough without turning away
because then you can well yeah the
first noble truth
this is suffering here
now this monks is the noble truth of
dukkha suffering birth
aging is took a death association with
the despised separation from the
loved not getting what one wants is
tooker in brief the five assumed aggregates
in brief the five assumed aggregates
yeah the five aggregates affected with
assumption so
basically your life is the basis for
your duka
that's it
it's not like particular things are
based for a dukkha the five aggregates
are basis for the dukkha
so you haven't done anything wrong in
other words
oh if only it didn't do that it was no
you were born birth is dukkha that's it
that's already
even if you don't do anything wrong
you're already effective it took because
you're already here
everything else that comes throughout
your life is kind of just a secondary
reminder of what the dukkha already is
and that you are already liable too
so that's that's again why why
a person needs to develop the state of
mind that
recognizes that
and basically restrains themselves from
trying to address the individual instances instances
of suffering
oh he said that which upset me she
didn't do that which upset me i'm going
to talk to her i'll tell him or to
address the suffering no
all of these things that you experience
throughout the life that makes you
suffer are not the reason for your
suffering if they were freedom from
suffering would not be possible
it's your craving in regard to how you
feel on account of these things in the
world that's the root of suffering but
for as long as you keep acting out
towards him or her or this or that or
particular instances of suffering you're
not allowing yourself to see it on the
right level which means you cannot
address it correctly
you're giving in you want to get rid of
it you still blame the individual
circumstances so that's when the view needs to be
so that's when the view needs to be
developed whereby you recognize that
it's not about
instances of suffering it's about the
fact that you are liable to suffer
that's it full stop
so
if it's not this instance the major
suffer it would have been something else
and it will be something else so you
trying to manage and perfect your ways
of managing your your environment
circumstances the way you speak to
people the way they speak to you all of
that is basically rooted in the fact
that you kind of deep down know that you
don't know the escape from suffering so
you just want to minimize the pain
you want to manage it
and for as long as you value the
management you will not force yourself
to look for the direction of uprooting
it
[Music] so that's why
so that's why
and that's the trap of oh it's helpful
psychotherapy is health psychology is
helpful all these managements are
helpful to manage the pain
to manage the pain
but if you become dependent on
management of the symptoms
you will not going to be able to endure
the symptoms
to reveal the source of your illness
because you immediately cover up the
symptoms you mentally you take the pill
you deal with the symptoms and it's gone
and now you don't see the illness
so you need to endure the symptoms
by not by resisting the pressure to
manage it which is already rooted in
that kind of i want to get rid of the
discomfort and by not managing
and by not managing
the discomfort you get to understand
right now is this they made me suffer
yesterday with that tomorrow with
something else the point is
i am liable to suffering and even if i
perfectly address this and this and that
i cannot prevent circumstances from
making me uncomfortable in the future
and that's the problem so you realize
it's not about particular sufferings
it's about nature of suffering i am
sort of infected or affected i am
affected liable
yeah exactly and these particular
instances of those
affections and infections are just the
reminders of my situation that's already
within that that's when
birth is already suffering but as in
manifestation you are manifested from
the moment you're born
so for as long as your manifestation is
here duke is here that's it
duke is here that's it
even as i said if you don't experience
anything uncomfortable no incidents nothing
uncomfortable no incidents nothing
nothing nothing sort of on the on the
level of the circumstances
you are still within dukkha you are
still liable and you still feel the same
thing if you look in that direction that's why
if you look in that direction that's why
you don't need great misfortunes and so
on to recognize the nature of situation
i am liable to suffer
yeah i'm affected by things i'm affected
yeah in you know things happen
i feel them exactly how do i feel them
well either feel them pleasant
unpleasant or neutral
which means
at any given time there is some pressure
basically placed on you let's say like
that so it's not like oh see now it's all
so it's not like oh see now it's all
fine i'm not affected by suffering well
are you feeling something yes to that
extent suffering is implicit in it
because you're liable to feelings
can you even conceive being in control
of your feelings
[Music] saying i shall feel this and i shall not
saying i shall feel this and i shall not
feel that no you can that's only like on
the level of wishful thinking
feeling is that symptom
exactly exactly so the fact that
you are not absolutely like you have you
have no say in what feeling arises and
how long it persists
and you know
that that
they change so now you have a pleasant
feeling you had it so many times before
but you also know that it has to cease
at some point
which means
it's most obvious
if you admit to yourself
that through sheer change of feeling
through sheer change of feeling
one which are feelings there you will
have to experience suffering
so are you able then
to not to be pressured by anything that
you feel at any given time
even pleasure because pleasure pressures
you know it makes you nervous what if i lose
know it makes you nervous what if i lose
this what if it doesn't last long enough
well i want more of it how do i protect
it how do i get it again
so it's not actually a peaceful state
pain obviously it's not a peaceful state
and then
neutral feeling boredom is very much not
peaceful although it's peaceful
but i mean okay so there's nothing
happening yet when nothing's happening it's the
yet when nothing's happening it's the
most frightening thing for the mind it's
like a numb pain yeah boredom brings
this dread brings terror yeah
[Music] just three types of feeling that's all
just three types of feeling that's all
you have that's all you ever had three
types of pain
well one type of pain pain of feeling
yeah three types of feeling means one type of
three types of feeling means one type of
pain one zuka
that's what sari would have said
whatever's felt counter-subconscious
suffering in the discipline of a noble
one if you have the right view if you
if you have the right view if you
understood the nature of feeling
feelings you understand that whatever's
felt is unpleasant because it's felt
so if you feel if you're
if you're
affected you you can know that
well you are
infected you have a disease
exactly yeah it's a symptom of an
underlying problem these are symptoms of
that disease that you know sometimes
it's hot sometimes it's yeah
there's sharp pains yes soft pains numb
yeah means you're subjected to it
you're it's not healed you are
imprisoned by it you you're you're
trapped within it you're confined and so
on
but if you don't see that as a symptom
as i said if you still
feel justified and have the view that
management of suffering management of
symptoms doing something about it to
overcome it when it arises
if you don't abandon that view and if
you don't restrain yourself
you're not going to see how deep it goes
which means you're not going to see the
source of it i'm a way of feeling
i'm in in a way aware of
well if you're aware of feeling
correctly if you're enduring the feeling
correctly if i want to find myself yeah
so like so that brings then the question
what is feeling
because most people would
again through those views of of
management proliferation and confusing
information for understanding
uh would kind of on the level of our
feeling are these like physical
sensations that i have in my body no
feeling is a state of mind feeling is
always mental
bodily feelings are always mental
[Music] and there's only three types of healing
and there's only three types of healing
on that level
which is the level of feeling
agreeable disagreeable and neither
agreeable nor disagreeable let's go to
the second noble truth and this monks is
the noble truth of the origin of the
girl the craving that makes for further being
the craving that makes for further being
exactly accompanied by passion the light
seeking the light here and there whose
translation is that uh i'm not sure
yeah they're further being i'm not sure
about anyway
so
what is it
it brings us basically to the point i
already said so it's
the origin of dukkha the source of
dukkha so the base is the necessary condition
so the base is the necessary condition
for presence of dukkha is presence of
tanha
is presence of cravings
so it's not what you've seen heard smell
taste touch thought about remembered
planned failed
it's about craving
tanha towards what's felt there and then
towards what's felt there and then
that's the root of dukkha
so the world samsara is not
not a suffering
it's not the cause of suffering
it's your attitude that on that
emotional level towards samsara that's
what suffering is so it's your craving
towards it that's what suffering is
what craving well craving for more
pleasure and pleasant feeling craving
for less pain in in painful feeling in
craving for uh ignorance and ignoring
and indolence in a neutral feeling
that's it that's the root of the entire
universe of suffering
but in order to get
onto the level of that root
you need to stop acting out of that
craving which is trying to manage your suffering
which is trying to manage your suffering
or pursue sensuality
or
constantly being distracted through
activities and avoiding boredom and
solitude that's all these prerequisites in the
that's all these prerequisites in the
form of lifestyle the good outline are
basically just ways of
rounding up
[Music] that that over the center of that
that that over the center of that
suffering which is your craving which is
that internal thing but if your
lifestyle still revolves around
you know sensuality
pursuing the further pleasure and the
kind of pleasure that you felt uh
management you're suffering getting rid
of acting out of pain
uh unwholesome acts uh of anger and
retribution and all of that
well there's no way you're going to
uproot suffering uh craving tanha
mentally when you're physically still
when you're physically still
passionately engaged passionately
engaging maintaining that maintaining it
keeping it alive
so first you physically need to stop
um acting out of it then verbally then
mentally you can eventually see see the
roots um see your own attitude towards
what's currently felt and that's what
the town high is
that that what i said before that trying
to trying to get rid of it trying
resisting resisting the currently during feeling
resisting the currently during feeling
by wanting more of it less of it or
neither of it none of it
wanted to switch it up wanted to change
it wanted to want to sort of
act out of it because you feel actually
confined within it so you need to endure
the confinement of the feeling and not
act out of it so you need to give up
sensuality when it's pleasant you need to give
when it's pleasant you need to give
management to pain when it's unpleasant
and you need to give distraction and
indolence when it's neutral
and that will result in a sense of
confinement and
and
deep fatigue and resistance that we
spoke before but if you don't act out of
it the mind will come down within that
and then you get to see for what it is
that's wisdom it's not a magical result
of
some method or or some
accidental insight or something
wisdom is just a development of strength
and non-resistance
on that internal level
and if you stop resisting stop flinching
stop looking away stop looking beyond
you get to see what's right in front of
you you remove that craving
you remove that craving
oh that's that's that's what removes you
don't remove the craving or actually
move it but if you stop
resisting it stop moving exactly
when you get the seed for what it is
then craving will sort of evaporate
because craving requires you to want to
look away or more of it or less of it
that's how you're maintaining it right
you you remove it indirectly exactly
yeah by not moving yeah
by not moving yeah
yeah by not providing a basis for
craving to move
the craving will sort of dry up
but not moving but not trying to switch
it off yeah
so the third noble truth this is the
noble truth of the end of suffering
the remainder is fading away the
cessation giving up relinquishment
release and letting go of that very
craving [Music] [Music]
so that's
cessation of craving means cessation of
possibility to suffer
on account of anything
that the senses the aggregates the world
brings you
good or bad doesn't matter you cannot
suffer because you cannot claim
you can't be moved you can't be moved
yet
and then the fourth noble truth
is
how to develop yeah how to develop that
cessation your playful path yeah
so that's what i mean the right well the
right view first
always comes first you need to know
right so
the root of the craving is not in the
world it's not in the sufficient management or
it's not in the sufficient management or
not you know
not a perfect technique or something
else it's in the craving towards what
i'm feeling my craving towards my
feeling nothing else
so first i need to stop acting out so
the livelihood needs to start matching
that principle you're trying to develop
the the speech needs to start matching
the principle then your efforts need to
start matching and that's normally the
path right view right mindfulness right
right view right mindfulness right
effort
and everything else that follows that
results then eventually like complete
immovability of the right kind on the
level of the what's being felt
so then in the pleasure they'll just be
pleasure felt there will be no more
craving or in like in
implicit craving for wanting more of it
it's just gone so it's just to extend
the feelings present there's nothing
more there's nothing less because you're
not resisting it nor leaning towards it
yeah it's not touching you
exactly it's not yours anymore
so you're not being touched by it which
means it's not pressuring you anymore
there's nothing wanted in regard to it
and nothing nothing not wanted in regard
to it either
so pretty much the noble ethopath is
everything we've been describing from
the beginning of this talk
it's not like oh i need to understand
one two three and then give me these
eight steps that i need to figure out
now understanding one two three is the
eight steps
is the noble eightfold path is the right
view